Finding Aid for Detroit, Mackinac & Marquette Land Company records, 1879-1919
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Detroit, Mackinac & Marquette Land Company records 1879-1919
Detroit, Mackinac & Marquette Land Company.
45 volumes
91424 BB
Successor to the Land Department of the Detroit, Mackinac & Marquette Railroad Company, owner of large land holdings in Michigan's Upper Peninsula. Timber surveys, applications to purchase company lands, and tax records.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated in 1944 by George P. McCallum (donor 1866 ), the president of the company.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Detroit, Mackinac and Marquette Railroad Company was established in 1879 to connect the Straits of Mackinac by rail with the iron mining region of Marquette County, Michigan. Through acts of 1873, 1874, 1875, 1877, and 1879, the state legislature had granted over 1,300,000 acres of state swamp lands to support the building of the railroad. The railroad was completed in 1881, but the line was not profitable, and the company was bankrupt by 1886. At that time, the land owned by the company was separated from the railroad. The railroad was consolidated into the Duluth, South Shore & Atlantic Railroad, while the land was held by a firm continuing the name Detroit, Mackinac and Marquette Railroad Company. The company continued in business under this name, as a land company, not a railroad, until 1913, when it was succeeded by the Detroit, Mackinac and Marquette Land Company. The land company remained in business until at least the early 1950s.
The record group consists of three kinds of record volumes: Timber surveys; Applications; and Tax books.
Subjects:
Detroit, Mackinac & Marquette Land Company.; Detroit, Mackinac & Marquette Railroad Company.; Forests and forestry--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Land use--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Railroad land grants--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Railroads--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.
- Timber Survey 1890-1919 (Volume 1)
  Timber survey (v. 1-32): This is a series of surveys of lumber on company-owned land in the Upper Peninsula of Michigan. These surveys show estimates of how much lumber of each type of tree appears on a given quarter section of land and the type of soil that appears there. Although most of this survey work was done in the years between 1890 and 1900, some was done as late as 1919.
  - Vol. 1, T42-47N, R1W
  - Vol. 2, T42-47N, R2W
  - Vol. 3, T42-47N, R3W
  - Vol. 4, T41-47N, R4W
  - Vol. 5, T41-47N, R5W
  - Vol. 6, T42-50N, R6W
  - Vol. 7, T42-50N, R7W
  - Vol. 8, T42-50N, R8W
  - Vol. 9, T43-50N, R9W
  - Vol. 10, T42-49N, R10W
  - Vol. 11, T41-49N, R11W
  - Vol. 12, T41-49N, R12W
  - Vol. 13, T41-49N, R13W
  - Vol. 14, T41-49N, R14W
  - Vol. 15, T41-49N, R15W
  - Vol. 16, T40-48N, R16W
  - Vol. 17, T39-48N, R17W
  - Vol. 18, T44-48N, R18W; T44-48N, R19W
  - Vol. 19, T44-47N, R20W; T44-47N, R21W
  - Vol. 20, T44-48N, R22W; T44-47N, R23W
  - Vol. 21, T42-47N, R24W
  - Vol. 22, T42-46N, R25W
  - Vol. 23, T42-51N, R26W
  - Vol. 24, T42-52N, R27W
  - Vol. 25, T42-52N, R28W
  - Vol. 26, T42-51N, R29W
  - Vol. 27, T42-49N, R30W; T42-46N, R31W
  - Vol. 28, T42-46N, R32W; T42-46N, R33W
  - Vol. 29, T42-46N, R34W; T42-46N, R35W
  - Vol. 30, T43-46N, R36W; T43-46N, R37W
  - Vol. 31, T42-47N, R1E
  - Vol. 32, T42-46N, R2E; T41-43N, R3E; T41-42N, R4E; T41N, R5E; T41-43N, R6E; T42N, R7E
- Applications (Volume 2)
  Applications (v. 33-40): These records show all of the applications of individuals to buy land from the railroad between 1879 and 1913
  - Vol. 33 1879-1887
  - Vol. 34 1887-1891
  - Vol. 35 1891-1894
  - Vol. 36 1894-1896
  - Vol. 37 1896-1898
  - Vol. 38 1898-1900
  - Vol. 39 1900-1902
  - Vol. 40 1902-1913
- Tax Books 1898-1915 (Volume 3)
  The Tax books (v. 41-45) show all of the taxes paid by the railroad on these lands between 1898 and 1915. These records are especially important because the financial problems caused by the inability to dispose of its land quickly enough led to the eventual takeover of this railroad by the Duluth, South Shore & Atlantic Railroad.
  - Vol. 41, T42N, R1E to T46N, R3W
  - Vol. 42, T47N, R3W to T47N, R9W
  - Vol. 43, T48N, R9W to T43N, R15W
  - Vol. 44, T44N, R15W to T47N, R22W
  - Vol. 45, T48N, R22W to T46N, R37W
- Maps 1898-1915
  - Map of the northern peninsula of Michigan [map]: showing location of the lands belonging to Detroit, Mackinac & Marquette R.R. Co. in the counties of Schoolcraft, Mackinac, Chippewa, Luce, Alger, Marquette & Iron, Michigan / drawn by Edward Molitor Detroit, Mich.: Lithographed by the Calvert Lith. & Engraving Co. [1892?], c1881., 109 x 257 cm.; Scale [ca. 1:160,000] (W89°00'--W83°28'/N47°00'--N45°33'); [M 4112 .U6G46 1892 M6 Out.]
    (MHC copy includes only western half (area west of Manistique); copy 1 annotated to show updated township boundaries (1890s), copies 2 and 3 include unidentified annotations.)
  - Map of the northern peninsula of Michigan [map]: showing location of the lands belonging to Detroit, Mackinac & Marquette R.R. Co. in the counties of Schoolcraft, Mackinac, Chippewa, Luce, Alger, Marquette & Iron, Michigan / drawn by Edward Molitor. Detroit, Mich.: Lithographed by the Calvert Lith. & Engraving Co. [1892?], c1881., 109 x 257 cm.; Scale [ca. 1:160,000] (W89°00'--W83°28'/N47°00'--N45°33'); [M Roll 58]
    (MHC copy includes only eastern half (area east of Manistique) annotated to show land owned and leased by Camp Newton Club.)
  - Map of the northern peninsula of Michigan [map]: showing location of the lands belonging to Detroit, Mackinac & Marquette R.R. Co. in the counties of Marquette, Schoolcraft, Mackinac and Chippewa, Michigan / drawn by Edward Molitor. Mich.: Lithographed by the Calvert Lith. & Engraving Co. c1881., 109 x 257 cm.; Scale [ca. 1:160,000] (W89°00'--W83°28'/N47°00'--N45°33'); [M 4112 .U6G46 1881 M6 Out]
    (MHC copy includes only eastern portion, showing most of Chippewa and Mackinac Counties, with annotations.)
  - Map showing location of lands belonging to Detroit, Mackinac & Marquette R.R. Co. [map]: in the counties of Marquette, Schoolcraft, Mackinac and Chippewa, Michigan / W. O. Strong, land commissioner; Rand, McNally & Co., engravers. Detroit, Mich.: Detroit, Mackinac & Marquette R.R. Co. [1882]., 109 x 257 cm.; Scale [ca. 1:160,000] (W102°--W62°/N53--N39°); [M 4041 .P3 1882 R3]
    (Panel title: Northern Michigan farming lands.)
  - Map showing location of the lands belonging to Detroit, Mackinac & Marquette R.R. Co. [map]: in the counties of Schoolcraft, Mackinac, Chippewa, Luce & Alger, in part Michigan / drawn by Edward Molitor. Detroit, Mich.: Detroit, Mackinac & Marquette R.R. Co. [1882]., 76 x 131 cm.; Scale [ca. 1:160,000] (W86°24'--W83°28'/N46°46'--N45°45').; [M 4112 .U6G46 1890 M6 Out]
    (MHC copy 1 annotated to show updated township boundaries (1890s) and land ownership of John Gleason and E. H. Hotchkiss.)
Related Material
A 1943 catalog of company lands is found in Lands and Timber owned by Detroit, Mackinac and Marquette Land Company (FB2/DM159/L263).
The papers of George P. McCallum, president of the company in the 1920s-1940s, contain some information about the company.